Finding Aid for the Collection of Turkish Manuscripts LSC.0896
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Title (Romanized): Tercüme-i Resehat-i aynü'l-hayat Uniform title: Resehat-i ayn el-hayat Title (English): The translation of Drops of the spring of life Alternative titles: ????? ????? ??? ??????, Rasha?at- ? ayn al-?ayat, Date: 1659; Manuscript number: 209; 328 leaves: paper; 200 x 120 mm. bound to 189 x 133 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Black Morocco with leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, bound in gilt borders, 1b illuminated. (Box 54)
- Title (Romanized): Nasihatü'l-müslimin Title (English): Advice for Muslims Alternative titles: ????? ????????, Date: 1714; Manuscript number: 210; 240 leaves: paper; 219 x 159 mm. bound to 218 x 154 mm.; Layout: Average 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black leather, inlaid, with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, occasionally enclosed in red borders. (Box 55)
- Title (Romanized): Zübdetü'l-kelâm fî mâ yahtâcü ileyhi'l-hâss ve'l-âmm Title (English): The cream of discourse in what both the masses and the elite need Alternative titles: ???? ????? ???? ????? ???? ?????? ???????, Date: [17--]; Manuscript number: 211; 330 leaves: paper; 212 x 144 mm. bound to 210 x 142 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, inlaid, with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 55)
  There are two records for a Vecdi who died in 1660. LOC record: Vecdi Abdülbaki, d. 1660 credits him with a poetic anthology, and Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. I: 461 record: Vecdi Ahmet Efendi credits him the present title.
  Islamic tenets and doctrines, on prayer, faith, learning, charity, etc.
- Title (Romanized): [Divan] Title (English): [Poetic anthology], Date: [17--]?; Manuscript number: 212; 158 leaves: paper; 193 x 113 mm. bound to 196 x 114 mm.; Layout: Average 20 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Brown leather, inlaid, with fore-edge flap, and yellow paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, occasionally enclosed in red borders; leaves missing from the end. (Box 55)
  Author identified by reference to Kâtip Çelebi's Kashf al- ?unun, as well as Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. II: 23 where his name is fully spelled Ulvî Mehmet Çelebi.
  Collected poems of the sixteenth-century Ottoman poet, from Istanbul.
- Title (Romanized): [Hâzâ kitab-i ferâiz] Title (English): [Here is the book of inheritance law], Date: 1490; Manuscript number: 213; 137 leaves: paper; 167 x 125 mm. bound to 168 x 125 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap; separating. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages underlined in red; notes added to the end; marginalia. (Box 55)
  A Turkish commentary on an Arabic book on the rules of inheritance.
- Title (Romanized): [Siyer-i Nebî] Uniform title: Kitab-i siyer-i Nebî: Büyük Islâm tarihi Title (English): [Biography of the prophet], Date: [15--]; Manuscript number: 214; 276 leaves: paper; 170 x 120 mm. bound to 168 x 125 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped; front board missing. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; original leaves in the beginning and end separated and rewritten in a later hand. (Box 55)
  Identity of the author from a 19th/early 20th century note scribbled on the cover, accepted by DP.
  Apparently Darîr's biography of the prophet Mu?ammad. Two volumes bound in one.
- Title (Romanized): Hediyyetü'l-ihvân ve atiyyetü's-s?byân Title (English): The gift of the brethren and the present of the boys Alternative titles: ???? ?????? ????? ???????, Date: 1689 March; Manuscript number: 215; 243 leaves: paper; 196 x 143 mm. bound to 195 x 148 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Pink and white cloth on boards; separated. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; insect damage. (Box 55)
  Author designates himself a preacher from Galata (al-wa'i? Ghala?awi).
  Treatise intended for instruction of the fundamentals of religion and legal obligations of Islam.
- Title (Romanized): Dürr-i meknûn ve s?rr-i masun Title (English): Hidden pearl and protected secret Alternative titles: ?? ????? ? ?? ????, Date: [16--]; Manuscript number: 216; 358 leaves: paper; 202 x 140 mm. bound to 201 x 144 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with blind-stamped leather strip over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; blank leaves near the end; ending missing. (Box 56)
  The author calls himself Seyyid Mustafa b. Hasan el-Hüseyni. Matching this author with the title is Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. III: 39-40.
  A universal history up to the reign of the Ottoman Sultan Murad III (1574- 1595), translated from the author's own Arabic original entitled Nihayat al-maram wa ba?r jawahir al-kalam.
- Title (English): [Religious poems], Date: 1730; Manuscript number: 217; 169 leaves: paper; 211 x 156 mm. bound to 210 x 146 mm.; Layout: Average 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with dark brown leather strip over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; leaves missing from the beginning; water damage. (Box 56)
  A collection of long rhyming poems (Mesnevis) on the prophets Joseph, Job, Muhammad, etc. The author of the first treatise occasionally refers to himself(?) with the pen-name Beygi (20b, 22b, 26b).
- Title (Romanized): ed-Dürrü'l-münazzam fî s?rr?'l- ismi'l-âzam Title (English): The arranged pearl in the secret of the most grand name Alternative titles: ???? ?????? ?? ?? ???? ?????, Date: 1678 March; Manuscript number: 218; 326 leaves: paper; 204 x 149 mm. bound to 208 x 157 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, back cover all but faded; with red leather strip over spine; and marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; quires almost entirely separated. (Box 56)
  Translation of an Arabic original entitled Mifta? jafr al- ja? wa mi?ba? al-nur al-lamí by Bistami (Abd al- Ra?man ibn Mu?ammad, ca. 1380-1454), undertaken by the order of the Ottoman Sultan Mehmet III (1595-1603). Apparently on charms and numerology.
- Title (Romanized): Dürr-i yetim Title (English): The rare pearl Alternative titles: ?? ????, Tercüme-i Cavidan-name, Date: 1639 Spetember; Manuscript number: 219; 268 leaves: paper; 194 x 125 mm. bound to 195 x 130 mm.; Layout: 24 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Burgundy leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; charts and graphs. (Box 56)
  A translation of a Persian text entitled Javidan'namah, on numerology and divination, apparently a Hurufi text originally composed by Náimi Tabrizi, Fazl Allah, 1340-1394 (see DP). A brief versified version of the same title, apparently by the same author, is appended to the end of the manuscript (ff. 265b-268a). A table of contents is at the beginning.
- Title (Romanized): [Müretteb-i deka'iku'l-hakaik] Title (English): [The exactitudes of truths well arranged] Alternative titles: [Murattab Daqa'iq al-?aqa'iq], Date: 1550; Manuscript number: 220; 178 leaves: paper; 192 x 128 mm. bound to 192 x 135 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Green cloth on boards with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; marginalia. (Box 56)
  The second part of the author's name may also be Alevi (as opposed to Ulvi). Kâtip Çelebi refers to him as "the poet".
  A glossary of Perso-Arabic terms into Ottoman Turkish, originally composed by Kemalpasazade (1468 or 9-1534) in 1533 (see reference in KZ), here rearranged by the author of the present manuscript.
- Title (Romanized): Gülsen-i râz[-i manzum] Title (English): Flower-garden of mystery [versified] Alternative titles: ???? ???, Tercüme-i Gülsen-i râz, Gulshan-i raz, Date: [15--]?; Manuscript number: 221; 89 leaves: paper; 192 x 128 mm. bound to 192 x 135 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; water damage; leaves missing from the beginning and the end. (Box 56)
  DP calls the author Elvan-i Sîrâzî (following a penciled note by a late 19th/early 20th century hand on the inside of the front cover), and dates the composition to 1417, i.e. during the reign of the ottoman Sultan Murad II (r. 1421-1451).
  A versified translation into Turkish of an original Persian text on Sufism by Shabistari (Ma?mud ibn Abd al-Karim, d. ca. 1320.)
- Title (Romanized): el-Kitabü'l-Müntahab min serhi'l-Gülistan Title (English): Selections from the commentary of the Rose-garden Alternative titles: ?????? ??????? ?? ??? ????????, al-Kitab al-Muntakhab min sharh al- Gulistan, Date: 1754; Manuscript number: 222; 220 leaves: paper; 212 x 162 mm. bound to 211 x 168 mm.; Layout: 31 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Black leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red. (Box 57)
  The present text is a selection of a commentary upon the Gulistan of Sádi. A note in the front endpaper attributes the original commentary to Bosnavîi Sudi (d. 1596 or 7). The author/scribe refers to the events in the year 1754, but a chronogram as well as actual digits at the end of the manuscript give the date October 1595, presumably the date of the original manuscript from which the copy or the selections were made.
- Title (Romanized): Tercüme-i Resehat-i aynü'l-hayat Uniform title: Resehat-i ayn el-hayat Title (English): The translation of Drops of the spring of life Alternative titles: ????? ????? ??? ??????, Rasha?at-i ayn al-?ayat, Date: 1812; Manuscript number: 223; 330 leaves: paper; 205 x 149 mm. bound to 202 x 152 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Faded black leather, blind-stamped, with torn-off fore-edge flap; marble paste-downs; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; extensive marginalia. (Box 57)
- Title (Romanized): Ta'bir-i [divan-i] Hâf?z Title (English): The interpretation of [the poetic anthology of] ?afi? Alternative titles: Serh-i divan-i Hâf?z, Date: [1600]?; Manuscript number: 224; 334 leaves: paper; 209 x 110 mm. bound to 208 x 112 mm.; Layout: 23 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown leather, inlaid, with fore-edge flap; burgundy paste-downs; gilt decoration. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b illuminated; extensive marginalia. (Box 57)
  Abdullah b. Hüseyn K?r?mî (front endpaper); Çelebizade or Halebizade (front endpaper)
- Title (Romanized): Menak?bname[-i Sa'ban Efendi] Uniform title: Menak?b-i serif-i Pîr-i Halveti Hazret-i Saban-i Veli; Risale-yi Türbename Title (English): The biography [of Sa'ban Efendi] Alternative titles: ????? ????, Manaqib'namah-i Shában Efendi, Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 225; 148 leaves: paper; 200 x 125 mm. bound to 196 x 121 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Blue marble paper on boards, with yellow marble paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; leaf 1 separated. (Box 57)
  Mehmet Tevfik (ownership stamp on front endpaper)
  A biography of the Halveti Sufi Saban-i Veli, d. 1569, composed during the reign of Ottoman Sultan Ahmet I (1603-1617). The manuscript contains a second title by the same author.
- Title (Romanized): Nakd-i hât?r Title (English): Money for the memory Alternative titles: ??? ????, Naqd-i kha?ir, Naqd al-kha?ir, Naqd al-khawa?ir, Date: 1654 May; Manuscript number: 226; 218 leaves: paper; 198 x 126 mm. bound to 201 x 127 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Brown and burgundy leather, blind-stamped, with fore-edge flap, and yellow paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 57)
  Müezzin(?) Sâlih (his signature on front endpaper)
- Title (Romanized): [Sir'atü'l-Islâm tercümesi] Title (English): [Translation of Laws of Islam] Alternative titles: ShiRat al-Islam, Date: [16--]?; Manuscript number: 227; 137 leaves: paper; 192 x 140 mm. bound to 190 x 140 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Fading green marble paper on boards. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; leaves missing from the end.
  Mehmet Sa'dullah (note on front endpaper)
  A translation of a treatise on the rules and doctrines of Islam. DP, following Karatay, Fehmi Edhem, Topkapi Sarayi Müzesi Kütüphanesi türkçe yazmalar katalogu, mss. 81, suggests that the present manuscript might be the commentary of Burusawi (Yáqub ibn Ali, d. 1524 or 5) on a text by Imam Zadah (Mu?ammad ibn Abi Bakr, 1097 or 8-1177 or 8). However, the first sentence of Burusawi's translation, quoted by Karatay, does not agree with the first sentence of the present manuscript. Kâtip Çelebi too quotes a number of commentators for an Arabic book of the same title, but the first sentence of none of them matches the present work.
- Title (Romanized): [Ebu Müslim-name]? Title (English): [The story of Abu Muslim]?, Date: [19th/early 20th century]; Manuscript number: 228; 138 leaves: paper; 240 x 170 mm. bound to 238 x 171 mm.; Layout: 19 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh, Nastál?q, and Riqa. Binding: Burgundy leather, with fore-edge flap, and green paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, occasional marked words in red; several hands. (Box 58)
  Bagdatizade Hüseyn Aga (signature and stamp on 1a and 2a).
  This is the first of a three volume work that seems to be the Turkish translation of the Persian Abu Muslim'namah of Abu ?ahir Tarsusi (Mu?ammad ibn ?asan), and begins with the tale of Ahmet Zemci. Ire`ne Melikoff, in her Abu Muslim, le "porte- hache" du Khorassan, dans la tradition epique turco-iranienne also refers to a Zemciname. It is a legendary account of Abu Muslim Abd al-Ra?man ibn Muslim (8th cent.).
- Title (Romanized): Makas?d-i aliyye fî serhi't-Taiyye Title (English): The sublime finales in the commentary of the Quest Alternative titles: ????? ???? ?? ??? ?????, Maqa?ad aliyah fi shar? al-ta'iyah, Date: 1886 April; Manuscript number: 229; 237 leaves: paper; 210 x 148 mm. bound to 210 x 150 mm.; Layout: 25 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Black leather, with fore-edge flap, and green paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, occasional marked words in red. (Box 58)
  A Turkish commentary upon the ode known as Ta'iyah written by Ibn al-Fari? (Umar ibn Ali, 1181 or 2-1235). Original composed in September of 1616.
- Title (Romanized): Münyetü'l-ebrâr ve gunyetü'l-ahyâr Title (English): The wish of the good and the wealth of the upright Alternative titles: ???? ?????? ????? ??????, Munyat al- abrar wa ghunyat al-akhyar, Date: 1776; Manuscript number: 230; 164 leaves: paper; 211 x 145 mm. bound to 209 x 141 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Marble paper on boards, with fore-edge flap, and yellow paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 58)
  Author calls himself Abd al-Ra?im al- Qara?i?ari ibn Ala' al-Din al-Mi?ri, also known as M?s?rl?oglu Abdürrahim Karahisarî.
  A treatise on Sufism, concerning the dicta of the sage Aksemseddin (1389 or 90-1459), composed during the reign of Ottoman Sultan Mehmet II (14441445, 14511481).
- Title (Romanized): [Serh-i] Mant?ku't-tayr Title (English): [Commentary upon] the Conference of birds Alternative titles: ??? ???? ?????, Shar?-i Man?iq al-?ayr, Date: 1690; Manuscript number: 231; 108 leaves: paper; 208 x 130 mm. bound to 205 x 134 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Marble paper on boards, with brown leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; marginalia. (Box 58)
  Form of author's name from Osmanl? Müellifleri, V. II: 394. The death- date is obviously wrong.
  A commentary upon the Persian mystical poem of Farid al- Din A??ar (d. ca. 1230), composed in April/May of 1597, during the reign of Ottoman Sultan Mehmed III (15951603) and dedicated to a certain Yeniçeri Agas? Hasan Aga.
- Title (Romanized): [Tercüme-i Vikayetü'r-rivaye fi mesaili'l-hidaye]? Title (English): [Translation of the Preserving of narratives regarding the issues of guidance]? Alternative titles: ????? ??????? ?? ????? ???????, Wiqayat al-riwayah fi masa'il al-hidayah]?, Date: 1581 February; Manuscript number: 232; 185 leaves: paper; 200 x 138 mm. bound to 200 x 141 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh and Nastál?q. Binding: Faded brown leather. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; water damage; leaves missing from the beginning. (Box 58)
  Connecting the author with the title using Kâtip Çelebi's Kashf al- ?unun under the original.
  The author gives the date 1424 and has dedicated the work to Ottoman Sultan Murad II (Murad II (14211444 and 14451451). But Kâtip Çelebi whose Kashf al-?unun has been used to identify the title writes that the author had done the translation in 1462 and dedicated to Ottoman Sultan Mehmet II (14441445, 14511481). If the same title, then this is a translation into Turkish verse of an Arabic original on religious doctrines and regulations composed by the fourteenth century al-Ma?bubi, itself being an epitome of a work by al-Marghinani (d. 1196 or 7).
- Title (Romanized): [Menâk?b-? serif-i Hünkâr Sultân Hac? Bektâs-? Velî Horasânî] Title (English): [The blessed life of Hünkâr Sultân Hac? Bektâs-? Velî of Khurasan], Date: 1764; Manuscript number: 233; 131 leaves: paper; 205 x 148 mm. bound to 205 x 148 mm.; Layout: 17 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh and Nastál?q. Binding: Black leather, with fore-edge flap, and black leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink; some leaves rewritten in a later hand and attached to the manuscript. (Box 58)
  A biography in verse of the thirteenth century Anatolian Sufi master Hac? Bektas Velî.
- Title (Romanized): [Divan ve Risale] Title (English): [Poetic anthology and treatise], Date: 1776; Manuscript number: 234; 37 leaves: paper; 207 x 154 mm. bound to 206 x 153 mm.; Layout: 11 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Water-damaged green paper on boards, with burgundy leather stripe around the edges. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders. (Box 58)
  The full name of the author is spelled Qu?b al-Arifin al- Uskudari al-Shaykh al-ayyid Yusuf ?aqqi.
  The collected poems of Yusuf Hakki, copied by one of his disciples after his death. The manuscript also contains a brief treatise in prose and verse by the same author.
- Title (Romanized): [Divan] Uniform title: Nâ'ili-i Kadim divâni Title (English): [Poetic anthology] Alternative titles: ????? ?????, Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 235; 137 leaves: paper; 210 x 159 mm. bound to 211 x 161 mm.; Layout: 11 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Beige paper on boards, with brown leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink; some water damage. (Box 59)
  Collection of the lyrics of the Ottoman poet Na'ilî. The gazels occur at the end of the book.
- Title (Romanized): [Divan] Title (English): [Poetic anthology], Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 236; 32 leaves: paper; 203 x 157 mm. bound to 210 x 163 mm.; Layout: 18 lines of text per page. Script: Riqa. Binding: Green cloth on boards, with gilt decorations, and pink paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink. (Box 59)
  Selection of the poems of Ganîzâde Mehmet Nâdirî, copied in a notebook from the 19th or early 20th century.
- Title (Romanized): Ravzatü'l-Islam Title (English): The garden of Islam Alternative titles: ???? ?????, Raw?at al-Islam, Date: No date; Manuscript number: 237; 81 leaves: paper; 203 x 157 mm. bound to 210 x 163 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Beige paper on boards, with brown leather stripe over spine. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; water damage; ending missing. (Box 59)
  A penciled note from the 19th or early 20th century as underlined and question-marked a phrase in the second hemistiches of the first verse of 6a as possibly the author's name (The full name being Muradî Âbidî. DP accepts this.
  A Turkish translation in verse of ShiRat al-Islam by Imam Zadah (Mu?ammad ibn Abi Bakr, 1097 or 8-1177 or 8). The original was composed in 1511, during the reign of Ottoman Sultan Beyazid II (14811512).
- Title (Romanized): [Serh-i Virdü's-settar] Title (English): [Commentary on the Rose of the one who veils] Alternative titles: [Shar? Ward al-sattar], Date: [18--]; Manuscript number: 238; 130 leaves: paper; 222 x 152 mm. bound to 222 x 155 mm.; Layout: 21 lines of text per page. Script: Riqa. Binding: Black leather, with gilt decoration; fore-edge flap; and green paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; 1b illuminated. (Box 59)
  A Turkish commentary on a Turkish text on the required deeds for all those who are on the [Sufi] path (83b) originally composed by Ömer Fuâdî, 1560-1636. This text is itself copied on the leaves following the commentary. The manuscript also contains several shorter tractae by Ömer Fuâdî, Abdullah b. Mehmet M?srî?, and Ibn al-Arabi (1165- 1240).
- Title (Romanized): [Serh-i risale-i Ustüvani Mehmet Efendi] Title (English): [Commentary upon the treatises by Ustüvani Mehmet Efendi] Alternative titles: [Shar? risalat Ustuwani Mu?ammad Afandi], Date: [17--]?; Manuscript number: 239; 52 leaves: paper; 217 x 158 mm. bound to 215 x 160 mm.; Layout: 15 lines of text per page. Script: Naskh. Binding: Beige leather; frayed. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red; water damage. (Box 59)
  A Turkish commentary on a treatise by Mehmet Ustüvani on faith, religion, prayer, ablutions, etc. A very short title, "Nasihet-i Iblis" [Advice of the Devil] is appended to the end.
- Title (Romanized): [Serh-i Eyyühe'l-veled] Title (English): [Commentary upon O, my son] Alternative titles: ???? ?????, Date: [17--]; Manuscript number: 240; 48 leaves: paper; 209 x 149 mm. bound to 208 x 155 mm.; Layout: 13 lines of text per page. Script: Nastál?q. Binding: Marble paper on boards, with burgundy leather stripe around the edges; fore-edge flap; gray paste-downs. Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, marked passages in red, enclosed in red borders; marginalia. (Box 59)
  Kâtip Çelebi says that a certain Emir Mustafa b. Ali known as Âlî had translated the Arabic into Turkish and had called it Tuhfetü's-suleha.
  A commentary and translation of a work entitled Ayyuha al-walad, originally in Arabic and by Ghazzali (1058-1111).